Register of the United States Army European Command, Historical Division Typescript Studies, 1945-1954
Hoover Institution Archives
- P-Series Manuscripts. (Box 34-59)
  - P-198 Measures Employed by Both German and Soviet Forces in Denial of Rail and Highway Transport Facilities, and Means Employed for Restoration. (In preparation--1954.) (Box 55)
  - P-200 German Army Training Methods and Maneuvers. By Generaloberst Franz Halder. (In preparation -1954.) (Box 55)
  - P-201* Personal Diary Notes of the G-4 of the German Ninth Army, 1 Aug. 1941-31 Jan. 1942. By Generalmajor Josef Windisch; 440 pp; 1953. An army-level G-4's day-to-day duties and problems; a transcript of a shorthand diary. Statistical data from this source has been used in MS # (Box 55)
  - P-202* They Significance to the Germans During World War II of the Allied Term "Unconditional Surrender." By Generaloberst Franz Halder. (In preparation--1954.) (Box 55)
  - P-203 German and Russian Operations During World War II against Permanent and Semi-Permanent Fortifications. (In preparation--1954.) (Box 56)
  - P-206 (Box 56-58)
  - P-207 German Exploitation of Arab Nationalist Movements in World War II. By Gen. D. Fl Hellmuth Felmy & Gen. D. Art Walter Warlimont. No description available. (Box 58)
  - P-209 Unknown (Box 58)
  - P-211 Weather Information for Army Tactical Operations. By Generalmajor Alfred Toppe and Others. No description available. (Box 59)
  - P-217 (Box 59)
- T-Series Manuscripts. (Box 60)
  This series was begun at Neustadt in July 1947 and last numbers were assigned in 1951, although most of the projects were either completed or cancelled by early 1949. Each topic was to be treated in broad terms by a committee of officers, one of whom was to act as topic leader. The topic leader was to supervise and edit the work of his colleagues. Since this program required considerable organization and cooperation and since many of the contributors were being released from prisoner of war status or transferred from Neustadt to other camps, few studies were completed as originally intended. Many individual contributions were forwarded directly to the Historical Division and processed separately. Many manuscripts intended originally as T-series studies eventually became part of the B-, C-, D-, of P-series. Consequently there are gaps in the numbering and many of the manuscripts have not been translated. Apart from MS # T-9, which is still in preparation by the author, all work on this series has been suspended. P-series manuscript titles are drawn from the Guide to Foreign Military Studies, 1945-54; Catalog & Index (Headquarters, United States Army, Europe, 1954)
  - T-19 Rear Area Security in Russia. By Oberst Hasso Neitzel; 39 pp, 2 maps; DA Pamphlet No. 20-240; 1951. Tactics of Russian partisans and German countermeasures. (Box 60)
  - T-26 The ZITADELLE Offensive,1943. By General der Infanterie Theodor Busse and 5 others; 209 pp, 23 illus; 1947. A short summary is supplemented by five annexes, describing the operations of Armeegruppe Kempf, Fourth Panzer Army, Ninth Army, and Fourth and Sixth Air Fleets. Includes comments on strategic planning and the difficulties encountered when two army groups are involved in a single operation. (In USAREUR only the topic leader's summary (40 pp.) is available in English.) (Box 60)
  - T-28 Battle of Moscow, 1941-42. By General der Infanterie Hans von Greiffenberg and 6 others; 271 pp, 37 illus. A survey of the operations of Army Group Center, pointing out reasons for the German failure. Attached studies describe the actions of individual infantry and armored corps. (In USAREUR only the topic leader's main study (119 pp.) is available in English.) (Box 60)
  - T-31 Collapse of Army Group Center 1944. By Generalmajor Peter von der Groeben; 79 pp, 7 illus; 1947. An account of the German retreat before an overwhelming Russian attack, including information on Russian methods of deployment for a major offensive. Describes German reconnaissance and other methods of detecting and evaluating Russian intentions. A brief appendix describes Russian partisan activity against railways in the army group communication zone. (Box 60)
  - T-34 Terrain Factors in the Russian Campaign. By General der Infanterie Karl Allmendinger and others; 60 pp, 6 maps, 6 photographs; DA Pamphlet No. 20-290; 1951. The salient geographical feature of central, western, and southern European Russia; terrain problems and how they were met by the Germans, examples of combat in each type of terrain. This study and MS # T-24 together cover the entire area of German operations in Russia. (Box 60)